Hey everyone and thanks for jumping back
into the macroverse.
Today we're going to talk about how the
rate cutting cycle is over and how the
rate hiking cycle has already begun. If
you guys like the content, make sure you
subscribe to the channel, give the video
a thumbs up, and make sure to check out
the report that I just published called
the balance of risks. The balance of
risks. And I it's for August 2026. If
you want to read it, it's completely
free. Just go to benjamancow.com
and go to the reports tab. And if you
scroll down, you'll find the balance of
risks report. And you can go ahead and
either put in your email to to receive
it directly to your inbox. Or if you
don't want to do that, uh you can just
scroll down and and read the PDF on the
website. And the goal is to help
communicate what are the different risks
that are currently going on. uh you know
in the in the overall economy and how
does that affect the markets especially
for the next uh several months. So
that's what the report is about. I would
encourage you guys to go uh check that
out. Now before we get into this video
and I'll probably do this for at least a
couple of videos just because you know
this is not really a crypto video. Um
but I did want to say thank you to
everyone for being a subscriber here. As
you guys know, I recently hit a million
subscribers. And uh just recently, I got
the 1 million subscriber uh plaque from
from YouTube. So, that's pretty cool.
And it's just kind of a reminder uh that
there are in fact people on the other
side of the screen that are listening.
Sometimes I just stare at this little
green dot on my uh on my um computer. Uh
but it's nice to see that, you know, we
hit a million subscribers, right? And I
think that's a pretty cool milestone to
hit and certainly one that I I never
really imagined hitting when I first
started the channel. When I first
started the channel, I just thought, you
know, when I had a 100 subscribers, I
was over the moon. Never could I have
imagined a million. But life throws you
curveballs. So
the the title of the video, you know,
about the rate cutting cycle as being
over, there's going to be a lot of
people that that disagree with that. A
lot of people that disagree. And it's
okay to disagree, right? I'm not, you
know, I'm not against people
disagreeing. It's okay. I'm going to get
things wrong. We're actually bringing a
lot of people together in November at
the ITC conference. And guess what? A
lot of us are probably going to disagree
on a lot of stuff, but the goal is to
kind of come together and and have a
rational discussion about it rather than
have everyone just simply agree with
each other, right? So again, ticket
prices are going up September 1st if you
guys want to check that out.
the rate cutting cycle for, you know,
for the Fed arguably ended a while back,
right? I mean, you can see the last time
we had a rate cut was in fact in 2025.
One of the things I don't know if you
guys remember, but I kind of speculated
dubiously in fact was that what if Trump
replaces Powell with someone else and
then that someone else that their first
move is to raise rates? You know, I
remember saying that some back in 2025.
And while that may or may not come to
pass, there is a realistic chance that
it in fact does. And it might the reason
why there's going to be a lot of dissent
right now in terms of like calling the
rate cutting cycle kind of over in the
short term is because,
you know, the labor market kind of
leaves a lot to be desired. If you were
to look at the last non-farm payroll
print, it wasn't that great if we're
being honest, right? If you were to look
at the employment level and the the
recent, you know, data point that we
got, we lost 23,000 jobs here in in the
States. Now, you can see that this has
kind of been plateauing for a little
while. And if you look at the
year-over-year change, you can see that
contractions in the US economy have
often coincided with this metric going
negative. Okay, it's not negative right
now, right? Like if you were to look at
it right now, you can see that it's
still technically positive. We've added
316,000 jobs um over the last
year, right? Over the last year, if you
were to look at a percentage change,
it's up about 2%. Again, it's not up a
lot, but it is still technically up. And
the stock market, the thing that it
absolutely loves to do is climb the wall
of worry, right? That's what the stock
market loves to do is just climb that
wall of worry and look for that pocket
of optimism, which is why I think the
stock market is is still fine right now.
But I would argue that we likely will
see the stock market get about a 10 to
20% correction starting. It could start
this month, but that's not my base case.
My base case is that it doesn't start
until next month. And it might not even
start till like the very end of next
month, in which case you won't even be
aware that it's starting until October,
right? Once we actually see the market
potentially uh go down. So if if the
employment level is so low, how can we
justify the rate cutting cycle being
over, right? Like it doesn't necessarily
make a lot of sense if you're just
looking at this metric. But the problem
is there's a lot of other things to
consider. And what a lot of people do on
on Twitter and on YouTube, they'll just
look at like one data series and then
try to, you know, come up with a
proclamation that the Fed has to do
something based on this one data series
and they'll ignore everything else,
right? There's been a lot of guys who
have been calling for, you know, massive
rate cuts for years and years and years
and years. Even in 2022, if you guys
remember when the Fed was raising rates
and it was October of 2022, there were a
lot of people, you know, going on these
interviews and and really criticizing
the Fed for having rates and not even
that high of a level, right? I don't
even remember exactly where it was, but
they weren't even that high back then.
Um, you know, near the end of 2022,
you're like 3% or something. But the
reason why people were upset was because
they were only using the stock market as
their gauge as to what the Fed should
do. But if the Fed had listened to the
armchair economists, then they wouldn't
have raised rates and we probably would
have actually had a much worse inflation
problem than we actually do right now.
So it's dangerous to use a single data
series to project out what the Fed
should do. So again, the the largest
dissents that you'll see from this view
are that the non-farm payroll level
isn't really doing that great right now.
But if you look at several others, like
if you look at initial claims, again,
they're still printing relatively low
levels, right? Like not not really a
concerning area right now. And in fact,
not that long ago, put in the lowest
level it's put at put in decades.
Additionally, the unemployment rate in
the United States, while jobs seem to be
going away, the unemployment rate has
actually been trending down for
basically the entire year. I mean,
November 2025 sort of marks the high on
the unemployment rate as it stands today
at 4.5% and it's just been slowly going
down since then and now you can see it's
actually at 4.1%.
So, it's true that we've we lost jobs,
you know, over the last over the last
month or whatever, but when you consider
that the unemployment rate has been
going down, it doesn't really seem like
it's filtering through to having these
adverse effects on the economy. And one
of the reasons for that is if you were
to look at the labor force participation
rate that that's actually been dropping
a lot, right? So, you know how the
unemployment rate peaked in November?
Well, the the labor force participation
rate has actually been dropping pretty
quickly since November. So, one of the
reasons why the unemployment rate isn't
higher is just because a lot of the
people that were looking for jobs back
in November just aren't looking for jobs
now. And again, I it affects things,
right? Like this affects what the
markets are going to do. It it affects
the reaction function of the Federal
Reserve. It affects a lot of things. And
if the labor force participation rates
falling off this quickly, it's going to
be hard for the unemployment rate to go
up in the short term unless layoffs
actually happen. Which brings me to the
last labor market report I can show you
here, at least probably for this video,
that shows you that layoffs, while
they've been generally trending up since
2021, are more or less still at
preandemic levels. Even I just I'm
already lying, right? Because I'm going
to pull up another one. If you look at
job openings, job openings, while they
were going down since 2022, they're
basically just normalized to prepandemic
levels. So, the issue is is that you
have sort of some conflicting reports in
the labor market. You have not as many
jobs and in some in some months job
destruction,
but the the the labor market isn't
really sending the same distress signals
that you would expect to accompany that.
the unemployment rates trending down,
job openings generally have been
trending up. Um it just hasn't been what
you would necessarily expect. And if you
look at something like the um the job
openings per unemployed worker, this is
a metric that Jerome Powell used to site
a lot. It went down into December 2025,
but then it's kind of bounced back up to
be more or less a little bit lower than
prepandemic levels. But pre but briefly
it actually went below one meaning there
were fewer job openings than available
workers. Now it's actually back above
one. So the risk here is that the Fed
actually has to raise interest rates
before they can ever lower them again.
That doesn't mean the Fed's going to
immediately raise rates a ton. We're
talking about a token 25 basis point
rate hike seems like a a likely outcome
to me. Anyways, it seems like a likely
outcome. Now, previously I've said that
it could happen as early as September or
I think it I I think it will likely
happen this year. It I think it'll
either happen in September or December.
It could be November, but with or
October, but with the midterms, you
know, right at the end of October, I
don't know if that's the the most likely
month. And so right now September or
December seem like Canada months um in
in which there would in fact be a rate
hike. Now you have to ask yourself if if
the denters are are so confident that
they're not going to raise rates, why
does the market the overall market think
they're going to? It's because there's
more than one data series that we have
to account for, right? There's not it's
not just one data series. And hopefully
by showing you the other data series,
you can be like, "All right, there is a
reason." Now, in the last inflation
print, right, in the last inflation
print, it actually came in not so not so
bad, right? If you were to look at at
headline inflation year-over-year, what
you'll see is that it actually has been
dropping uh since that since that kind
of scary read back in in May of 2026.
But arguably, if you were to look at the
price of oil, some of that drop was was
sort of from this move by oil where oil
was going back down into, you know, into
July. But recently, oil's actually kind
of gone back up a little bit, which
makes me wonder, there's going to be
some lag here, right, in terms of energy
prices and how it then affects overall
CPI.
But because oil's back up, it does make
me think that inflation is not
necessarily completely conquered uh just
yet. Think about, you know, the the
labor market getting tighter in some
ways. In other ways, a little bit
looser. It it it makes sense that
there's a risk of a rate hike. there's
not like a confirmation that the Fed's
going to raise rates. But the problem, I
would argue, is if the Fed does not
raise rates, then the long end of the
old curve will likely scream higher and
the bond vigilantes will likely revolt
once again. For a long time, you know,
I've been adamant that the 30-year yield
was going to break to new highs.
If you guys remember back in October of
2023,
30-year yield hit about 5.2%.
And ever since then, after that drop,
ever since then,
what's happened? They issued shorter
duration than the market was expecting,
and there was a big sell-off. But the
thing, the problem now is that yields
are heading higher, right? The long
end's heading higher. And I I put out
something on Twitter about this not too
long ago, and I got yelled at by a lot
of a lot of macro gurus for saying that
that, you know, these yields could go
higher. But the problem is, look,
there's, even this week, the 30-year
yield is still heading higher. And I
think there's a lot of people that just
don't have confidence that the Fed's
going to do what they need to do. We
don't really have forward guidance in
the way we used to have it. I think
Kevin Wars already came out and and sort
of speculated that maybe the long end
could just handle this stuff for them.
The long end, you know, the bond, the
bond market doesn't like this, right?
The yields are likely heading higher.
The 30-year is likely heading higher.
The 10-year yield is likely going to
head higher. It's already back up to
4.7. I think it's going to head up to
about 5%. So, yields, in my opinion, are
likely heading higher. And and when
yields are going up, what it generally
means is that the market is more worried
about inflation reacelerating right now
rather than an imminent recession. If we
were going into a recession, yields
would likely be dropping because then
the market's worried about future
growth, not inflation. So yields are
starting to trickle back up.
And one of the reasons is because
inflation is not necessarily completely
conquered yet, back down to 2%. Kevin
Wars is adamant they'll get it there.
But while he's saying that they're going
to get it there, he's not really
providing any type of forward guidance
or discussion about rate hikes that
would give us the confidence to know
that they're actually going to do that.
If, for instance, they were just so
leave rates where they are now,
would that really be enough to tackle
inflation? The rest of the world doesn't
really seem to think so. And and this is
kind of where the the video title comes
from. We talk a lot about the Federal
Reserve and it makes sense that we do
because a lot of the markets that I talk
about on this channel, you know, are
more so closely monitoring what the Fed
is doing than other central banks around
the world. But other central banks
around the world in a lot of places have
already started the rate hiking cycle.
If you were to look at interest rates,
you'll see that the United States,
the Fed, hasn't moved rates since last
year. But if you were to look at the
Euro area, like Europe, they already
raised rates, right? Like you can see
they already raised rates a few months
ago. If you look at Australia, you can
see they started raising rates earlier
this year. If you were to look at some
of these other ones, I don't know if
Yeah, Canada hasn't started, but Japan
has been raising rates for a while, and
they're probably going to keep raising
rates because the 2-year yield in Japan
keeps going higher. If you look at New
Zealand,
New Zealand interest rates are going up.
By the way, some of you are from New
Zealand. And I say that because I'm
actually speaking at a at a tech
conference in New Zealand next month.
So, uh hopefully I'll see some of you
guys there. Um I'll put a link to that
in the description below in case
anyone's interested in attending. But
again, it's it's all the way down in in
New Zealand. Uh but you can see that
they've they actually already raised
rates.
The UK has not yet. Uh, China hasn't,
but a lot of them have, right? Like a
lot of them have already started raising
rates and and so I guess the question
becomes
will
will the US eventually follow, right?
Will the US eventually follow? a lot of
these other countries don't think that
didn't think that rates were were high
enough and and so they just even though
they went through this rate cutting
cycle they've already started to raise
rates again. I think there's a good
chance something like that could happen
once again. The reason why this is not
so clear-cut is because if you were to
go look at at interest rates um you know
in the United States like if you if you
were to go look at at at Fed the Fed
funds rate going back through a lot of
different business cycles like look at
the '9s. You see how they raise rates
and then they cut rates
and then in 97 they like raised rates
again, held there for a while and then
cut and then raised and then the the
recession finally hit. But you see how
long that took. And if you if you
decided not to buy stocks in 1996
because, you know, because you were
worried about a rate hike, well, I mean,
look like overlay the S&P.
Look at look at the stock market back in
96. Yeah, you got a rate hike. The stock
market got a little correction and then
it went much higher. And by the time it
came back down into that recession, you
would have actually been better off just
simply buying stocks in in 1997 before
the rate hike than waiting because the
stock market when eventually the rec
recession occurred, the stock market was
at a higher level then uh than it was
just before that rate hike. So again, a
rate hike is not the end of the world. A
lot of people assume that it is. They
assume that that the stock market has to
collapse and and never recover if
there's another rate hike. But in
reality, a rate hike implies that the
economy is still doing okay. So while in
the short term a rate hike might be a
little scary,
it's not really the scariest thing
because what it implies is that things
are actually okay. when the Fed is panic
is is panicking and cutting rates.
That's usually when the market is
falling apart, not when they're
contemplating a rate hike, which is
exactly what they're contemplating right
now. So, I can't tell you exactly when
it's going to occur. I think they should
do it sooner rather than later if
they're going to. I'm not really sure
that waiting until December makes that
much sense. Uh but they might. I would
argue it's probably going to happen this
year and then after they raise rates, my
guess is that they're then just going to
hold at 4% for a little while. Kind of
like in the 90s when the Fed raised
rates um you know, they raised rates
from like 5.25, they raised them up to 5
1/2 and then they left them at 5 1/2 for
a while, right? They left them there at
5 and a half for over a year, like a
year and a half essentially. So that is
that's my read on on what's going on
right now. And and that is ultimately
sort of how I see this playing out. I
see I I see the stock market getting
about a 10 to 20% drop starting in
likely not until September,
but it not being a recession, right? It
could, but it's not my base case. It
being a drop that allows Bitcoin to find
its market cycle bottom. People get
scared because the Fed's raising rates
and then all of a sudden the next the
next market cycle begins and then the
people that got scared because the Fed
were raising rates are all of a sudden
left wondering like why did they get
scared for the Fed raising rates? The
Fed raised rates a lot in 2023 and 2024
and the stock market did just fine. Yes,
we are later cycle now than we were back
then. But I I' as I've said for a while
the this part of the cycle can last for
years before before things finally, you
know, before the business cycle has to
or potentially end. So I think for now
the argument is that the rate cutting
cycle is over. Not just in the United
States, but also many places around the
world. The rate hiking cycle has already
begun. And you can see that's happened
in in it's already started in in several
different countries. What I also did was
we're looking now this chart is a GDP
weighted policy rate. Not based on every
single country, but if you want to just
pause the video, you can read the
description and you can see like what
countries are included. And in this
case, you can see that recently um the
GDP weighted policy rate has actually
been slowly climbing. And that's a
reflection of the fact that there are
central banks now that are in fact
starting to raise rates. So that's where
we find ourselves. It's not as scary as
it sounds. Although it might lead to a
brief correction a little bit later in
like late Q3, early Q4, but if history
is any indication, there's a good chance
that's just going to be another
opportunity for those that have the
patience to invest through the cycles.
Okay. And again, we have the first
investing through the cycles conference
coming up in November. The main
conference day will be November 21st.
We'll probably have like an event uh
we'll have an event like the night
before, maybe just sort of like a meet
and greet type thing and then we'll have
something, you know, um we'll have
obviously a lot going on on the 21st and
then we'll everyone will be checking out
on um the 22nd theoretically and flying
out. But the conference is coming up uh
in November. Main date November 21st.
access the main data to mark your
calendar to be there. And again, ticket
prices are going to go up on September
1st. So, if you are planning on going
and if you have not already gotten your
ticket, I would encourage you to go
ahead and get it before the ticket
prices in fact go up. Thank you guys for
tuning in. Subscribe. Give the video a
thumbs up. Remember to check out the
report I just published called The
Balance of Risks. Links in the
description below in the pin comment.
And I'll see you next time. Bye.